In her TED Talk, the astronomer Merced uses a range of stylistic techniques to bring a very complex, very abstract subject vividly to life.
What does she do? She starts out by telling a story.
It’s almost like a children’s story. “Once there was a star. She was born…”
On it goes, charting the life of this star, the death, and then the rebirth as a supernova.
It’s a way of making something almost beyond our comprehension comprehensible. She makes it real. She makes it human.
That kicks her off. Then she gets into the more technical part of the story, where she’s talking about the energy, the scale, the dimensions.
She compares the amount of energy
to the amount of energy that the sun burns in ten days.
That helps us conceive of something that we could never understand if she told us how many trillion kilojoules it was.
Similarly, she compares the magnetic field
to that of the Earth. I think it was a thousand trillion times bigger than that of the Earth.
And that helps us conceive of these huge numbers in a way
the actual number itself would be meaningless for us.
So she starts using the stylistic techniques of her physical presence, of her vocal emphasis,
to bring this stuff to life, to underline where the important points in her message are,
because it’s difficult stuff she’s talking about. We need her to help us in this way.
Think about how she puts the vocal emphasis in her sentences on particular words. “A tremendous amount of energy.”
“An itty-bitty, tiny portion of the electromagnetic spectrum,”
and that was matched to a tiny little gesture. And then there are the big gestures. She talks about the spinning star, spinning
faster and faster, and she uses, with her words,
the analogy of the ice skater, and she illustrates that with her arms. We see it happening.
And then she talks about the whirling matter being dragged around.
So she’s bringing it to life using vocal emphasis, using physical gestures, and using vivid analogies and compelling simple stories.